Ruth Clifford Engs papers, 1947-2010 C404
Indiana University Archives
- Research, writing and professional activities files, 1963-2015; undated (Box 1)
  - Published Essays and Articles, 1971-2014 (Box 3)
    - L'Utilisation de l'hypnosea afin de reduire les problems lies au stress chez le parent isole, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Drug abuse hysteria: The challenge of keeping perspective, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Warning Labels on Alcoholic Beverages, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Do Warning Labels on Alcoholic Beverages Deter Alcohol Use?, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Controversies in the Addition's Field: Volume One, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Resurgence of a New 'Clean Living' Movement in the United States, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Drinking Behavior: Taking Personal Responsibility, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Mass Hysteria or Toxic Fumes? A case study for University Administrators, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Women, alcohol, and health: a drink a day keeps the heart attack away?, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Using Magic for AIDS Prevention: Some Teaching Techniques, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Using Magic for Aids Prevention, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Forbidden Fruit, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Protestant and Catholics: Drunken Barbarians and Mellow Romans?, 2000 (Box 3)
    - St. Scholastica: Finding Meaning in Her Story, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Fashion Corner, 2009 (Box 3)
    - Beginners Luck, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Corsets and Girdles of the Model A Era, 2013 (Box 3)
    - Permission List for published articles, monographs, and book chapters, 2014 (Box 3)
  - Published Research Articles, 1963-2002 (Box 3)
    - Precipitation and recovery of sindbis virus, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Origin of the protein of sindbis virus, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Are we teaching them what they want to know?, 1971 (Box 3)
    - The characteristics of volunteers in crisis intervention centers, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Health knowledge of crisis intervention volunteers, 1976 (Box 3)
    - The drinking behavior of college students and cognitive effects of a voluntary alcohol education program, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Let's look before we leap: The cognitive and behavioral evaluation of a university alcohol education program, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Drinking patterns and drinking problems of college students, 1977 (Box 3)
    - College students' knowledge of alcohol and drinking, 1977 (Box 3)
    - The drug-use patterns of helping-profession students in Brisbane, Australia, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Again – let's look before we leap: The effects of physical activity on smoking and drinking, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Drug-taking patterns of health care students in Brisbane, 1981 (Box 3)
    - The drinking patterns and attitudes towards alcoholism of female tertiary helping professional students in Brisbane, Australia, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Medical, nursing, and pharmacy students' attitudes towards alcoholism in Queensland, Australia, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Drinking patterns and attitudes toward alcoholism of Australian human-service students, 1982 (Box 3)
    - College students' drinking problems: A national study, 1982-1991 (Box 3)
    - A survey of drug use and attitudes toward drugs among male law students and police trainees in Queensland, Australia: A research note, 1983 (Box 3)
    - The health concerns of young American and Egyptian: A cross cultural study, 1983 (Box 3)
    - The health concerns of students and the implication for alcohol education programming, 1983 (Box 3)
    - College students' drinking attitudes: 1970-1982, 1984 (Box 3)
    - College students' attitudes toward drinking – 1983: Exploring socialization theory, 1984 (Box 3)
    - A pilot study for exploring an innovative technique for attitude modification, 1984 (Box 3)
    - The drinking patterns and problems of college students: 1983, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Health concerns over time: The apparent stability, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Use of progressive relaxation and hypnosis to increase tennis skill learning, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Correlates of drinking problems among collegians, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Age-specific alcohol probation and college students' drinking problems, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Religion and collegiate drinking problems over time, 1987 (Box 3)
    - College students' drinking patterns and problems, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol, tobacco, and caffeine and other drug use among nursing students in the Tayside Region of Scotland: A comparison between first- and final-year students, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Drinking problems among Jewish college students in the United States and Israel, 1988 (Box 3)
    - University students' drinking patterns and problems: Examining the effects of raising the purchase age, 1988 (Box 3)
    - College women, 1989 (Box 3)
    - The alcohol knowledge and drinking myths of a national sample of university students, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Reactance theory: A test with collegiate drinking, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol knowledge and drinking patterns of nursing students over time, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Black college students' drinking patterns, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Family background of alcohol abuse and its relationship to alcohol consumption among college students: An unexpected finding, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Gender differences in drinking patterns and problems among college students: A review of the literature, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Influence of religion and culture on drinking behaviors: A test hypothesis between Canada and the USA, 1990 (Box 3)
    - The drinking patterns of American and Polish university students: A cross-national study, 1990 (Box 3)
    - College students' drinking problems: A national study, 1982-1991, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Drinking games and problems related to drinking among moderate and heavy drinkers, 1993 (Box 3)
    - The student alcohol questionnaire: An updated reliability of the drinking patterns, problems, knowledge, and attitude subscales, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Boozing and brawling on campus: A national study of violent problems associated with drinking over the past decade, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Do traditional Western European drinking practices have origins in antiquity?, 1995 (Box 3)
    - The association of alcohol consumption with self-reported illness in university students, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Collegiate drinking: administrator perceptions, campus policies, and student behaviors, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Construct validity and re-assessment of the reliability of the health concern questionnaire, 1996 (Box 3)
    - The drinking patterns and problems of a national sample of college students: 1994, 1996 (Box 3)
    - The drinking behaviors of a sample of university students in Nanning, Guangxi Province, People's Republic of China, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence – Cycles of social reform: Is the current anti-alcohol movement cresting?, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Correlates of Alcohol, tobacco, and marijuana use among Scottish postsecondary helping-profession students, 1997 (Box 3)
    - The effect of religion and religiosity on drug use among a selected sample of post secondary students in Scotland, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Reduction of Consumption Theory: A test using the drinking patterns and problems of collegians in the United States, 1983-1994, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol use and abuse among youth, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Past influences, current issues, future research directions, 2001 (Box 3)
    - College students, alcohol, rape: Some demographic patterns, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Drinking practices and patterns among collegians, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Dissertation & Master's Thesis, Essays, Encyclopedia Entries, and Pedagogical Publications, 1970-2012 (Box 3)
    - The Health Concerns of College Students Enrolled in the Spring Term, 1970 (Box 3)
    - The personality traits and health knowledge of crisis intervention volunteers in the state of Tennessee, 1973 (Box 3)
    - 5 entries for temperance encyclopedia, 2001-2003 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol in the Encyclopedia of Wellness, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Health Reform Crusades of the Progressive Era with an Under Current of Eugenics, 2009 (Box 3)
    - Irving Fisher,, Cora Stoddard, Reformed Men's Clubs, Committee of Fifty, Scientific Temperance Federation, in Alcohol and Drugs in North America, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol, Blood Pressure, in Encyclopedia of Wellness, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Non-Research Presentations, 1971-2012 (Box 3)
    - Medical aid station: A demonstration project, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Values clarification: A practical base for gaming in health education, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol education on the college campus: Where should the focus be in the 1980's?, (roughly 1980) (Box 3)
    - Teaching responsible drug and alcohol use, 1980 (Box 3)
    - A youthful alcohol abuse prevention program in a rural American community: A grass roots project, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Using hypnosis to reduce stress related problems of single parenthood, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Intervention skills for health educators, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Teaching anyone to instigate a substance abuse intervention, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Hypnosis: Women & Health, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Hypnosis & Health Workshop, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol Education on the College Campus, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Predicting student drinking patterns and problems: Implications for program planning, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines for developing alcohol education programs in university settings, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Drinking and Thinking – Film (related materials), 1985 (Box 3)
    - Hypnosis and health workshop, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Hypnosis health and human services, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Hypnosis and Health Workshop, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Identifying co-dependency among university students, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Needs assessment and evaluation information requested for baseline data and evaluation for campus alcohol education programs, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Outline for campus policies, education, and evaluation, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines for developing alcohol abuse prevention and education programs for college women: A brief overview, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Women: Alcohol and other drugs, 1989 (Box 3)
    - How to develop prevention programs on the college campus, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Campus alcohol programming – Eta Sigma Gamma FIPSE Planning Conference, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol and other drugs program for teachers, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Hypnosis and health, 1990 (Box 3)
    - How to live with a critical care personality, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Burn out and stress prevention ideas, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol and other drugs: self-responsibility, 1991 (Box 3)
    - The resurgence of a new 'clean living movement': does its anti-alcohol aspect have origins on the past, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol and health, 1992 (Box 3)
    - It is healthier to drink moderately than to abstain: A politically incorrect statement in America's third clean living cycle, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Health magic and mind reading, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Using magic for HIV prevention, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Health magic and mind reading, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Magic in good health, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Health magic – General, Mid-1990s (Box 3)
    - Guidelines for Developing Alcohol Abuse Prevention Programs, 1996 (Box 3)
    - The clean living movement: the politics of alcohol, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Clean living movements and alcohol, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Prohibition movements, drinking patterns, and promoting sensible drinking among college students: A focus on women, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Hypnosis and health, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Weight control & hypnosis, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Ohio grape wine short course, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Responsible use of alcohol, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Chicago Recovery Alliance – Keynote Address, 2000 (Box 3)
    - 'Clean living' movements: American cycles of health reform, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Unseen Upton Sinclair Lecture, 2001-2009 (Box 3)
    - Upton Sinclair: Gossip, Scandal, and Health Fanaticism, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Research Conference Presentations, 1977-2014 (Box 3a)
    - Does Alcohol Education Work, 1977 (Box 3a)
    - A national study of drinking patterns among university students, 1979 (Box 3a)
    - The effects of participating in physical activity on smoking and drinking patterns, 1980 (Box 3a)
    - The drug taking patterns of medical, nursing, and pharmacy students in Brisbane, Australia, 1981 (Box 3a)
    - Medical, nursing, and pharmacy students' attitudes toward alcoholism in Queensland, Australia, 1981 (Box 3a)
    - The drug taking patterns and attitudes towards alcoholics of Australian women helping professional students, 1981 (Box 3a)
    - Attitudes towards alcoholism and the recreational drug use patterns of helping professional students in Queensland, Australia, 1981 (Box 3a)
    - International alcohol & drug abuse: The approach to treatment, 1982 (Box 3a)
    - The health concerns of students and the implication for alcohol education programming, 1982 (Box 3a)
    - What does the Health Concern Questionnaire Tell Us, 1982 (Box 3a)
    - The use of Ericksonian hypnosis for young female single parents, 1983 (Box 3a)
    - Drinking patterns and attitudes of university students: Implications for program planning, 1984 (Box 3a)
    - Predicting drinking related problems of college students, 1984 (Box 3a)
    - Mean knowledge score of the 1985 sample of university students from every state in the Unites State which have not changed drinking laws since 1974 (Box 3a)
    - The use of progressive relaxation and hypnosis to increase tennis skill learning: A pilot study, 1985 (Box 3a)
    - The recreational and medicinal drug use patterns of nursing students in the Tayside Region of Scotland, 1985 (Box 3a)
    - Alcohol knowledge among college students: 1983-1985, 1986 (Box 3a)
    - Comparison of IU students to large national sample of university students as to drinking patterns and drinking problems, 1986 (Box 3a)
    - Correlates of drinking problems and knowledge of alcohol among collegians over time: Implications for education, 1986 (Box 3a)
    - Co-dependency check list: A tool for prevention, intervention, and treatment, 1987 (Box 3a)
    - Correlates of drinking problems between various college majors: implications for identifying problem drinking among students, 1987 (Box 3a)
    - Knowledge of alcohol among college students: Implications for education, 1987 (Box 3a)
    - The code: A short questionnaire for identifying codependency among university students, 1987 (Box 3a)
    - Decrease in drinking-driving problems of university students over this decade: Implications from the health belief model, 1987 (Box 3a)
    - Drinking patterns and problems in college women, 1987 (Box 3a)
    - Reactance Theory and Drinking Legislation, 1988 (Box 3a)
    - Relationship between Co-dependency and Drinking Problems: A Negative Result, 1989 (Box 3a)
    - Drinking Games Among Moderate and Heavy Drinkers, 1993 (Box 3a)
    - Alcohol, Tobacco, and Marijuana consumption, 1996 (Box 3a)
    - Religion and Religiosity, 1996 (Box 3a)
    - Alcohol, Tobacco, and Marijuana use patterns among Scottish Higher Education Students, 1996 (Box 3a)
    - Better Babies and Fitter Families, 2006 (Box 3a)
    - Historiography of Margaret Sanger, 2012 (Box 3a)
    - Outline for the two lectures on the History of Public Health, 2013 (Box 3a)
    - Historical Research Seminar for School of Public Health, 2013 (Box 3a)
    - Margaret Sanger, Birth Control, and the Eugenics Movements, 2014 (Box 3a)
    - Trends in college students' drinking problems since 1982, 1988 (Box 4)
    - University students' drinking patterns and problems: Examining the effect of raising the purchase age with implications for educational programming, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Alcohol knowledge and drinking patterns of nursing students 1983-1985: Implications for nursing education, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Drinking patterns of nursing students over time, 1983-1987: Implications for nursing education, 1988 (Box 4)
    - The code: A short questionnaire for identifying codependency among university students, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Revalidation of the health concern questionnaire, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Legislation drinking norms: Their impact on collegiate drinking, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Using the CODE: A reliable 11 item questionnaire to predict co-dependency among college age students, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Assessing higher education co-dependents, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Comparison of the percent of drinking students who exhibited behavior related to drinking during 1987-1988, 1989 (Box 4)
    - College women drinking patterns: Implications of race and religion, 1989 (Box 4)
    - American and Canadian university students' alcohol use and associated problems: implications for public policy, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Controversies in the addictive field, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Polish and American university students' drinking patterns: A cross-sectional cross-cultural study, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Is the 21 year old purchase law contributing to underage alcohol abuse?, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Romanization and drinking norms: A model to explain difference in Western society, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Is public policy effective in reducing the drinking problems of American university students?, 1992 (Box 4)
    - American cycles of prohibition: Do they have roots in ancient drinking norms?, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Trends in American female nursing student's drinking problems over the past decade, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Drinking game playing and demographic characteristics: A cross-sectional study with a national sample of light-moderate and heavy drinking collegians, 1993 (Box 4)
    - American students with Scottish, Irish, and Scots-Irish and other Caucasian ancestry and their drinking patterns and problems related to alcohol abuse, 1994 (Box 4)
    - The health concerns of helping profession university students in Nanning, Guangxi, People's Republic of China, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Drinking patterns among students with Scottish, Irish, and other ancestry: Diversity among a Caucasian sample, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Using magic in the school health program, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Demographic characteristics associated with non-consensual sex among college freshmen, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Has the American clean living (anti‑alcohol) movement crested?, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Correlates of drinking, tobacco, and cannabis among Scottish post secondary students, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Clean living movements and alcohol, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Drinking across the Atlantic: Are Scottish students similar to American?, 1996 (Box 4)
    - The relationship between smoking and low grades among male students: has much changed in a hundred years?, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Stalking the determinants of behavior: from boozing student to clean living movements, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Lucy Page Gaston – forgotten anti-smoking crusader, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Stalking the detriments of behavior: From drunken students to chaos theory, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Model of Research, 1989-2002 (Box 4)
  - Published Books and Book Chapters, 1974-2015 (Box 4a)
    - Health Games Students Play (Box 4a)
      - 1974 (Box 4a)
      - 1975 (Box 4a)
    - Teaching Health Education in the Elementary School, 1978 (Box 4a)
    - Teaching Health Education in the Elementary School: Instructor's Manual, 1978 (Box 4a)
    - Responsible Drug and Alcohol Use, 1979 (Box 4a)
    - Women College Students: Drinking Patterns and Problems in Alcohol Abuse Problems Among College Students, 1986 (Box 4a)
    - Alcohol Policies and Practices on College and University Campuses, 1987 (Box 4a)
    - Alcohol and other Drugs: Self-Responsibility, 1987 (Box 4a)
    - The Code Manual: Using the Code Checklist for Determining Co-Dependency Among University Students, 1988; (2 folders) (Box 4a)
    - Personal Health: Study Guide and Lecture Notes, 1989 (Box 4a)
    - Personal Health: Study Guide and Lecture Notes Second Edition, 1992 (Box 4a)
    - Personal Health: Study Guide and Lecture Notes Third Edition, 1997; (2 folders) (Box 4a)
    - Controversies in the Addictions Field: Volume One, 1990 (Box 4a)
    - Black College Students' Drinking Patterns, 1990 (Box 4a)
    - Women: Alcohol and Other Drugs, 1990 (Box 4a)
    - Drinking Behavior: Taking Personal Responsibility, 1994 (Box 4a)
    - Construct Validity and Re-Assessment of the Reliability of the Health Concern Questionnaire in Advances in Health Education, 1996 (Box 4a)
    - Health Hints: Lecture Outline and Readings for Personal Health Students, 1999 (Box 4a)
    - Clean Living Movements: American Cycles of Health Reform (Box 4a)
      - 2000 (Box 4a)
      - 2001 (Box 4a)
    - Past Influences, Current Issues, Future Research Directions, 2001 (Box 4a)
    - The Progressive Era's Health Reform Movement: A Historical Dictionary, 2003 (Box 4a)
    - The Eugenics Movement: An Encyclopedia, 2005 (Box 4a)
    - Unseen Upton Sinclair, 2009 (Box 4a)
    - The Field Hospital that Never Was, 2015 (Box 4a)
  - Book Files, 1991-2001 (Box 5)
    - Clean Living Movements: American Cycles of Health Reform, 1991-2001 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1991-2001 (Box 5)
        - YMCA –, 1998 (Box 5)
        - Philip Ross, Forbes –, 1999 (Box 5)
        - Reviews –, 1996-1999 (Box 5)
        - John Burnham –, 1996-1999 (Box 5)
        - General -, 1991-2001 (Box 5)
      - Publicity, undated (Box 5)
      - Book Sample, undated (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5)
      - First Draft, 1999 (Box 5)
      - Second Draft, 1999 (Box 5)
      - Page Proofs, 1999 (Box 5)
      - Draft with Corrections, 1999 (Box 5)
    - The Field Hospital that Never Was, 2014-2015 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence concerning permissions, 2014-2015 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence with Booklocker.com, 2015 (Box 5)
      - Prospectus, 2015 (Box 5)
      - Draft, 2015 (Box 5)
    - The Progressive Era's Health Reform Movement: A Historical Dictionary, 1998-2002 (Box 5)
      - Contract, 1998-2002 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence and Reviews, 2001-2002 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 5)
      - First Draft - Part 1, undated (Box 5)
      - First Draft – Part 2, undated (Box 6)
      - Third Draft, 2001 (Box 6)
      - Fourth Draft, 2002 (Box 6)
    - The Eugenics Movement: An Encyclopedia, 2002-2014 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence with Editors, Archives, and Libraries, 2004 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence with Editors, Potential Reviewers, Colleagues, 2004 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence with Editors, Reviews, and Production, 2004-2005 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence with Indexer, Editors, Reviewers, and Colleagues, 2005 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, Eugenics debates and questions from media, 2005 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, Eugenics in Indiana and Indiana colleagues, 2005 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, New Eugenics Encyclopedia, 2007 (Box 6)
      - General Correspondence, 2002-2005 (Box 6)
      - General Correspondence, 2003-2005 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence with Editors and Reviewers, 2006 (Box 6)
      - General Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 6)
      - List of Entries and Changes, Figures, 2002-2004 (Box 6)
      - Reviews of Manuscript (Box 6)
      - Permissions, 2002-2003 (Box 6)
      - First Draft, 2004 (Box 6)
      - Second Draft (Box 6)
      - Third Draft, 2004 (Box 6)
      - Third Draft – Second Copy, 2004; (1 of 2) (Box 6)
      - Third Draft – Second Copy, 2004; (2 of 2) (Box 7)
      - Page Proofs, 2005 (Box 7)
      - Fourth Draft, 2005 (Box 7)
      - Eugenics clippings, 2005 (Box 7)
      - Better babies in rural south central Indiana: An examination of health and culture. New Frontiers project proposal, 2005-2006 (Box 7)
      - Eugenics, IU Mini-University, 2006 (Box 7)
      - Eugenics, Immigration Restriction and the Birth Control Movement, 2011-2012 (Box 7)
      - Eugenics, Immigration Restriction and the Birth Control Movement (Chapter 16), 2012-2014 (Box 7)
    - Unseen Upton Sinclair, 2007-2010 (Box 7)
      - General Correspondence, Including IU Entities, 2007-2009 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 2007-2010 (Box 7)
      - Printed Material – John Weidman/Sinclair Estate, 2007-2009 (Box 7)
      - Permissions, 2007-2009 (Box 7)